cold plunging is one of the coolest
trends right now and for good reason it
can help speed up muscle recovery as
well as offering mental benefits such as
assisting you in combating anxiety while
you can absolutely hop into a bathtub or
a trash can full of water and ice
companies like the plunge and polar
monkeys are turning this frigid activity
into a luxury experience but is one
better than the other
let's dive in and find out
what's up everybody it's jake back at
the barbing garage gym for today's video
i'm gonna be comparing two cold plungers
for y'all i have the brain pod from
polar monkeys and while i don't have it
with me i'm gonna be comparing this one
to the plunge cold plunge and help you
decide which one is best for you but
before i get going with any of that i
got to let you know we've reviewed a lot
of cold plunges on barbin.com and if you
want to browse our best list just go
ahead and search barbind best cold
plunges and you can find out for
yourself which one cracks that number
one spot okay so if you don't know what
cold plunging is well it's essentially
exactly as it sounds you're plunging
into cold water preferably colder than
59 degrees for around three to four
minutes to really get that full effect
all right so the similarities between
these two cold plungers now let's start
with the fact that both of these tubs do
feature a chiller located on the side of
the tub that's going to control and
regulate your temperature that way your
temperature is going to stay exactly
where you want it 24 7 and you don't
have to mess with any bags of ice which
is really nice
now there also is a filter on either
side of these tubs it's going to keep
your water pretty clear for the most
part you still might want to use some
type of chlorine or any other type of
chemical just to help you out and that's
really nice too because you don't have
to drain your water after every single
usage but if you want to you definitely
can
the drain located on the back of the tub
has a hose hookup that way you can
direct all your water away from all of
your electrical wiring you know which
for your own safety that's a nice touch
and you know lastly here with the
similarities you don't have to do
anything
extraordinary just to accommodate for
the power needed to run one of these
tubs since they only require a standard
110 volt outlet to be operated
okay so let's talk about the differences
now between these two cold plunges i'll
dig into all the models that are
available from each company in just a
minute but for now just know that this
brain pod from polar monkeys is listed
right around 3 500 bucks while the base
model of the plunge is listed around 4
now why is that such a big gap i mean
both companies offer a product that's
nearly identical i mean they both have a
pump a chiller and a filter on the side
so i'm thinking it has to do with the
materials that are used so this brain
pod is made from fiberglass while the
base model of the plunge is made from
acrylic which could technically last you
longer but you know with polar monkeys
all your models feature hot water with
temperatures reaching 103 degrees while
with the plunge you're gonna have to pay
extra for that hot water so in my
opinion you're really getting a bargain
with polar monkeys
okay so let's talk about the money
starting with the plunge once again the
base model is going to cost you around
thousand dollars on the hot and cold
version of that base model it's gonna
cost you around fifty five hundred bucks
the cold punch pro is listed right
around six grand while the hot and cold
version it's gonna run you around sixty
five hundred bucks and it's also worth
mentioning that these pro models do
feature a chiller with three times the
amount of power as that base model
xl version of the cold plunge is gonna
cost you around seven thousand dollars
while the hot and cold xl model is gonna
cost you around seventy five hundred
bucks and when it comes to the
commercial models it's worth mentioning
that they come with a one-year
commercial warranty as well as an even
more robust pump so the base commercial
plunge is going to cost you around 6 500
bucks while the commercial xl that's
going to run you around 7 500
also worth mentioning with these
commercial plunges that they don't
feature hot water so it's definitely
gonna be best to keep those indoors
during the cold winter months
[Music]
okay so with polar monkeys you also have
multiple models for you to work with but
remember this brain pod is listed right
around 3 500
now you do have two different steel tubs
for you to work with the portal and the
portal le which stands for limited
edition they both feature the same
dimensions but with the portal you can
either have it be regular steel or to
feature a black coating on it now that
four foot long regular steel model of
the portal is going to cost you right
around 2 200 bucks while that six foot
long regular steel model it's gonna run
you around twenty four hundred dollars
the four foot long black one that's
gonna cost you around twenty seven
hundred dollars while the six foot long
black one that's gonna run you around
twenty nine hundred dollars so the
portal le only comes in black with a
monkey graphic on it which honestly i
think looks pretty sweet
that four foot long model is going to
run you around 2 800 bucks on a six foot
long model let's go under around 3 200
now when it comes to the star treatment
model
it's around eight thousand dollars which
is a pretty big price gap but the cool
thing is you know your pump filter
everything's inside the framework of the
actual model itself which is really cool
makes it look cleaner it's probably
easier to you know assemble and install
everything as well
plus you can control everything from
your phone you can set your temperature
settings from your phone which might
make it worth that more luxurious
experience
okay so let's talk about the build now
with the plunge the base model weighs
150 pounds when it's empty and right
around a thousand pounds when it's full
and once again all the models are made
from acrylic but unfortunately i don't
know how much those xl models weigh i
would imagine they weigh more than 150
pounds when they're empty though now the
base model is five and a half feet long
it's right around three and a half feet
wide once you factor in the plumbing and
the chilling and it's right around two
feet tall so you could be able to fit
this you know on the majority of patios
maybe even in your garage but if you
were to go for that xl model you're
gonna have to accommodate a lot more
space because it's 11 and a half feet
long
five feet tall and five feet wide
you could run into spacing issues with
either one of these models that you
decide to go with
so you know if that is a really big
problem for you i would probably just
suggest looking for a company that
offers an ice bath that kind of looks
like a barrel but in my opinion i don't
know if that's the optimal choice
because i think that if your legs aren't
extended you know you could lead to some
heat pockets and that could keep you
from experiencing the full effect from a
cold plunge
also remember the pro models do feature
a chiller with three times the amount of
power and the commercial models feature
a more robust pump and they come with
that one year commercial warranty
[Music]
okay so let's talk about the accessories
that come with your plunge it does come
with an insulated cover as well as
guided videos on how to properly cold
plunge a cell phone holder is going to
clamp directly to the tub and that might
be you know might enhance your
experience a little bit and prevent you
from thinking about the cold water that
you're currently sitting in you do have
a 20 micron filter and that's going to
filter your water every 10 minutes this
can be really nice for any large debris
and help keep your water crystal clear
but if there's anything that's lingering
around it does come with a skimmer net
that way you can just scoop some stuff
out by hand if you need to and you know
since you do use a garden hose to fill
this up
a lot of times as a garden hose just
sitting outside
debris can get in there dirt grass
whatever it may be so they do have a
filter that attaches to your garden hose
and that's going to keep any of that
from getting in your tub as you fill it
up you do have the option of adding on a
water maintenance package it's a six
month package it's on their website for
right around 190 bucks that's going to
include six filters a 16 ounce baqua spa
sanitizer a 32 ounce bakwa spa oxidizer
a 16 ounce alkalinity up a 16 ounce ph
down as well as 25 testing strips if you
like to cold plunge at night i think
you'll enjoy the underwater lighting and
you know the plunge also uses ozone
enriched water which might be better on
the skin while also killing microbes
just as effectively as chlorine
[Music]
okay so let's talk about the build now
with these polar monkey plunges and
remember that's gonna change depending
on which model you decide to go with so
with this brain pod you know it's made
from fiberglass it's five and a half
feet long just under two feet tall and
with the plumbing and the chiller it's a
little over four feet wide it weighs 140
pounds when it's empty and right around
600 pounds when it's full now if you go
with one of the portals remember you
have the portal le and the regular
portal the dimensions don't change you
have two different options four feet
long or six feet long only thing that
changes is that with the regular portal
you can have it be regular steel or
black while with the le you know it's
only black with that monkey graphic on
there the four foot tubs are right
around 100 pounds when they're empty and
about 800 pounds when they're full while
the six foot tubs are 120 pounds when
they're empty and up to a thousand
pounds when they're full the star
treatment model is made from wood it's
seven feet long two feet wide two feet
tall and remember you're plumbing in the
chiller everything's within the actual
framework of the tub itself which is
really cool so this one's gonna weigh
right around 340 pounds when it's empty
and i don't know how much it weighs when
it's full but i think it's pretty safe
to assume that it weighs well over a
thousand pounds when it is full okay so
unlike the plunge polar monkeys does not
include any additional accessories with
your purchase so if you're interested in
the gfci cord the insulated cover the
smart plug and the ozone generator
you're gonna have to add those on
separately if you don't know what a gfci
cord is don't worry i didn't know what
that was either at first essentially
your plunge is gonna go into that cord
and then that cord is gonna go into your
outlet and that's going to prevent any
electrical shock or fire from happening
i would suggest adding that on it's only
35 bucks or so so it's not too bad i
just go ahead and get it if you're
plunging outside you know i highly doubt
you want grass or bugs or anything
getting inside your tub so i definitely
go ahead and get that insulated cover
it's going to cost you right around 450
bucks and that's also going to be nice
in terms of keeping your temperature
where it's supposed to be
ozone generator that's going to help
keep your water clean so i'd probably go
ahead and get that too it's around 400
and the smart plug is probably the most
non-essential thing out of all of these
you don't have to have it if you don't
want it it's going to allow you to set a
timer and a schedule to turn your plunge
on or off every day but you can't
control the temperature settings so i
don't know if you really
need that it can be around 55 bucks or
so if you choose to get it and if you
ever need to purchase any additional
parts for your existing plunge you can
definitely do so so let's say you need a
new hose to connect the pump and the
chiller it's going to cost you around 50
bucks a new chiller is going to be
around 2 grand and a new pump is going
to cost you around 100
and instead of having a light built into
the tub like with the plunge polar
monkeys tosses in a submersible light
literally just toss it into the plunge
and it's going to add a little bit of
ambiance to your plunging experience it
comes with a remote
a bunch of different color settings
right here for you to customize and it
requires three aaa batteries just simply
twist this apart you know put those in
there twist it back and you're good to
go
[Music]
okay so once again you know i do not
have that base model from the plunge but
i do have the brain pod from polar
monkeys so let's do a quick lap right
here we're gonna take all this insulated
cover it's gonna be super nice keeping
all of your water temperature in there
whether that be hot or cold as well as
keeping any debris bugs anything from
getting in there but on the front you
know you do have that pretty sweet
monkey graphic i was talking about i
just think it looks good and it brings a
little bit of originality to this cold
plunge makes it pretty unique in my
opinion okay so as you look in the
bottom right here you do see that drain
located right smack dab in the middle on
the side here you also have a jet it's
going to keep that water circulating and
keep everything from being stagnant plus
i got my toys right here that makes
everything more fun right
if we come around back you know aside
from this being made from fiberglass and
the plunge being made from acrylic
one of the main differences here is how
much is exposed and how much room this
takes up so with the plunge you'll have
a piece of plastic right here
and that's going to cover your filter
and your cords really everything
all that's exposed right here with polar
monkeys and another thing
this chiller is pretty big it's pretty
significantly bigger than the one from
the plunge that's okay though and this
thing you know this goes up to 103
degrees while that base model with the
plunge does not and this goes down to 36
degrees while the base model of the
plunge goes down to 39.
now
all of your electrical stuff is going to
go in here nice and waterproof it's
going to keep everything nice and safe
your ozone generator as well as really
just all your plugs right here this is
going to be really essential in my
opinion now originally all those cords
are going to be housed in this black box
right here that's still going to be
effective it's still going to prevent
water from getting in there for the most
part but i would still recommend just
using this this is going to be more
effective in my opinion and just more
safe overall now if we keep coming
around right here you will see your
filter as well as your pump that's
connected to the chiller from this black
hose and similar to the plunge
you have a hose hookup right here on
your drain that's really nice you know
you don't want a bunch of water being
all around all of your stuff right here
especially this pump so all you have to
do is just and this goes with the plunge
as well all you need to do is simply
screw on your hose to this hookup and
then just twist it and all that water is
going to be diverted away from
everything here which you know once
again for your safety is a really nice
touch
[Music]
okay so which brand should you go with
honestly you can't go wrong with either
one of these companies it's really just
gonna boil down to how much money you're
willing to spend as well as what
material you want your plunge to be made
from
from the chillers to the filters pretty
much identical and if you opt in for one
of the more expensive models from the
plunge they pretty much feature the
exact same temperature settings polar
monkeys just gets three degrees colder
but remember
the plunge also charges significantly
more for their models other than the
star treatment model so if you're
wanting to save some money i mean you're
probably going to go want to go with
polar monkeys and if you don't care if
it's made from steel you're going to go
want to go with the portal because
you're going to end up saving over 2 000
even while adding on all the accessories
and if you go for the brain pod you're
still gonna be saving over a thousand
dollars
which goes a long way but you know you
could also argue that you know if you're
gonna be outside plunging and a lot of
people are
acrylic might be the way to go which
would lead you to go with the plunge all
right y'all that's all i have for you
today on this comparison between the
plunge and polar monkeys like i said you
really can't go wrong with either one of
these companies
they make cold plunging as easy as
possible all you have to do is set up
your equipment toss in your hose to fill
up the tub with water set your desired
temperature and really you're good to go
really not much else to it end of the
day it's really just going to boil down
to how much money you're willing to
spend and what material you want your
plunge to be made from or if you really
even care at all thanks for watching
everybody i hope this video was helpful
and i was able to answer some questions
and really show the similarities and
differences between these two cold
plunges as always stay on the lookout
for my next review but for now why don't
you head over to barbin.com and you can
read more on these products and this
comparison just search barbind the
plunge versus polar monkeys review and
you can find everything we discussed
here today i'll see y'all next time
[Music]
[Applause]
you